Hello Taiwan, my name is Stefan Hofer, and I love a good story.
So imagine it was 20,000 years ago.
It is in the middle of winter and the tribe of cave people sit around a warm fire.
It is quiet except for the cracking firewood,
then one of the elders clears their throat.
Many summers ago,
a large herd of bison wandered through our hunting grounds
It was the largest herd that anyone had ever seen.
And as the elder shares his story one of the cave people starts to use colorful rocks and coal to paint a picture.
And to this very day, we can see this picture in the cave wall.
In the sense that is what we want to do with the Domain Storytelling.
We want to spark a fire, tell a story and paint a picture.
Storytelling is at the heart of human communication and it still works in the age of software.
Domain storytelling is one of the techniques that brings domain experts,
product owners, business analysts, and software development teams together.
It helps them to overcome misunderstandings
and to establish a common language
that helps you to talk about business processes and requirements
or in short to build better business software.
Today, I'm going to introduce you to Domain Storytelling by showing you a short demo.
then I will explain the method
and finally, I will tell you a little bit about the influence that
DDD had on Domain Storytelling and maybe also the influence that
DDD has that Domain Storytelling has on DDD in its community.
So I will tell you another story.
This time it is about a software system
that my colleagues and I built a couple of years ago.
It's a software system that was supposed to help approve roadwork.
So what happened was with a group of stakeholders
and they already had a set of requirements.
They said the system must support issuing permits
and the sector system must support hearings,
and we need support on reviewing applications and
many more use cases.
so the problem was that we didn't really understand how all these
isolated requirements make up a whole software system
for for proving roadwork we hadn't really understood the basic business processes behind it
so how does a proving roadwork typically work
that was the questions that we asked our domain experts
when we brought him together in a room
and in front of a whiteboard
and this is the story that holders.
So construction company has won a tender for a roadwork project
and before they can start they need to obtain a permit so that they can close the road to traffic
so the story starts where the project supervisor awards the contract to the construction company
and then they can submit the application for the permit using this new software system that we were supposed to build
now the stakeholders told us that the project supervisor should be notified
whenever a new application comes in because they need to review the application
and compare it with the tender documents
We didn't understand that requirement at first
and they explained us well there can be
for example different dates in the application than in the tender documents
if for example the construction company doesn't have the necessary resources
or maybe the weather has changed
then they need to delay the construction work
and that's why dates could differ in the application for the permit and in the tender documents
so once the application is reviewed
another role comes into play a traffic authority
they draft the permit
and they determine the concerned authorities for a hearing
so concerned authorities
those are for example: police, communities, public transport,
everyone who could be affected by a construction site
and they get a link to the hearing documents
and can review the permit
and they can submit statements
where they say either it's okay or they can raise concerns
like maybe they have a marathon planned or something like that
that would have an influence on the construction site
So the traffic authority then considers these statements and issues the permit
and the permit is then sent to the construction company
Now this whole hearing process here and drafting the permit
and revising the draft considering the statements made by the concerned authorities
that is something that can be repeated several times
but in this story we looked at a happy path scenario
so everything is fine
the first draft becomes the final permit
and this is often a typical way
of using Domain Storytelling we start with a happy path and then later look into a more complicated variations of the process
So this little story and visualizing that story helped us to understand in much more detail
what the system was supposed to do
and this is one of the typical cases for using Domain Storytelling to think about
new software systems and how they should support business processes
Now, how does this method work
Many people especially software developers tend to think about
business processes and visualize business processes like this
as a rather abstract but complete description of everything that could possibly happen
So it's about different paths in one picture
With the main storytelling we choose a different approach
We think that a good example is better than a bad abstraction
So we want examples first and from that knowledge from that foundation we can later build abstractions in our software
so usual usually it's sufficient to model two or three of the most important versions of the business process so the happy path maybe an important variation or common error scenario
so if we look at individual paths
and therefore we don't need any
any gateways or switches or ifs or case statements in our pictographic language
Now domain stories can have different scopes
The story that I showed you about the construction site was
I would say about medium on a medium level of detail
To give you some more idea how domain stories can can look I'll introduce you to another example
this time it's about a movie theater
so on the left side we see the process of going to the movies
so this is a end-to-end business process from the customer's point of view
so we have a moviegoer here they buy a ticket
from a cashier and then you buy snacks and drinks from a concession stand
and they showed a ticket to the usher to get access to the movie theater and so on
On the right side we see a much more detailed picture
that tells you the story of buying tickets we have a moviegoer
who picks seats and buys for the tickets and so on
so time buying tickets was one step in the course grade story on the left
and it's now a whole story on its own in the more detailed story on the right
and that's just one way of illustrating different scopes of stories
now no matter the level of detail or the scope of the story you will always need a pictographic language to visualize it
So our pictographic language is comprised of a set of symbols
So we have actors, the person or the people or the software systems
who are active in the story who do things
and we have work objects those are the things that they use it can be information, physical things
digital objects with activities depicted as arrows and we use textual annotations
now to give those icons a concrete meaning we label them so we have a customer ticket bias and so on
and if we look at the pictographic language in a little bit more detail
we can have for example different actors so most commonly
we use a single person, a group of people, a system but depending on the domain
that you're in you can change and adapt the set of symbols
for example I did a couple of the main stories in
in the harbor domain
so ships are important actors there and then have a little ship icon that represents a ship
the same is true for the work objects we also use different icons there
most commonly to express the medium of a book object
so for example if I call the cashier in the box office of the cinema and ask about a reservation for a movie tonight
and then I would draw this with a telephone icon
if they then send me a reservation as an email. I will use this email icon
and if I decide to print the reservation at home. I will use the document icon
with that pictographic language we can build sentences and the idea is that
the sentence in the pictographic language reads almost like
you would write a natural language sentence
now to tell a story we of course need more than one sentence
So what do we do. We append sentences and we express the order by numbering them
So that's how you find your way through the domain story
now the pictographic language is just one aspect of the main storytelling
equally if not more important is that it is also a workshop format a way of bringing people together
and what happens in the minds of the participants of the bookshop
is very important so it's the picture is not just it's not the only result
also being there being present in the workshop
if you miss this campfire experience it's not the same just looking at the result
showing the picture to someone who was not at a workshop
that's not the same as actually being there and contributing to it
so what do we need for a workshop. well we need people to tell us a story the story tells
and what is a storyteller without someone who listens so we need listeners
our storytellers are usually the domain experts, users stakeholders
and our listeners are usually members of a development team,
business analysts, usability experts and so on.
And often we don't have just one storyteller but we have several storytellers so every role that is involved in a business process can contribute to the story
Now storytelling is not just a one-way activity. It's more of a dialogue of a discussion.
So storytellers or domain experts are not always born storytellers
so they needs a little help that's where moderator comes
comes in handy and also the listeners can ask questions to move disturbing forward
So typically we would ask what's happening next or how do you know that you have to do this now
or where do you get the information from to write it down somewhere and so on
so we want the vivid conversation that moves forward
and while the story is told it is important that it is also visualized
and that's again a job that the moderator has
So we visualize the story using the pictographic language while it is told
so that gives everyone a chance to see if
we understood the story correctly or after any mistakes in it
so what will happen is that the domain experts so tell us say "oh no you missed a step"
or "no that's not what I said I used a different word" or "can you draw the arrow to... can you turn it around this is wrong"
so this is very available and immediate feedback that we get
for that to work everyone needs to be able to see the visualized story
so we use tools for that for example we can use
whiteboards and sticky notes or digital blackboards
or we could use the tool that I used to show you
the old work story it's called "Egon.io" it's open source runs in your browser
you can check it out egon.io is also the url.
Now there's a lot more of course to discuss and learn about Domain Storytelling
I've written a book about this method together with my colleague Henning Schwentner
so if you are curious go and check out domainstorytelling.org you will find all sorts of links there including links to the book
and you can even save some money if you buy directly from Edison Wesley via the informant store
You can use this coupon code "DOMAINSTORY" and get a nice discount.
Now how has Domain Storytelling influenced DDD and how is DDD influenced Domain Storytelling
Well, so far I haven't really talked about DDD.
In fact I've barely even talked about software or developing software or modeling software
and that is because Domain Storytelling
is a modeling method that helps you to have meaningful conversations about business processes
So building software for this processes is just one of many use cases for the main storytelling
you could use it to analyze weaknesses and problems
or you could use it to help newly hired employees to learn about your business
People do that and are happy with it.
However I mostly use it in software development projects
and there are some projects where I use Domain Storytelling like this
so I would start with analyzing
the domain analyzing the problem spaced as-is situation
modeling it together with the domain experts so they get a couple of domain stories out from that
It is something that we can learn from get feedback from
We used it as a basis to design a new improved process software supported process
We model that with to-be domain stories that show us the future situation
Again we get feedback from that
we use that to derive requirements
on a course grade or a medium grade level for example user stories or use cases
and again we get feedback on those requirements
and then we build software and of course we develop it iteratively and incrementally
that means we only take a couple of those requirements and refine them
and when you go to the next sprint iteration we take
another set of requirements and refine them so it's a constant process of refinement
Now this process is or this description of software development
is not entirely wrong but it's certainly not completely right
It's a bit too waterfally for me and that changed with domain driven design
In more and more of my projects, I get to use DDD.
And Eric Evans provided his own metaphor for the software development cycle.
That metaphor is the model exploration whirlpool and it looks like that.
So the whirlpool metaphor suggests that there are interconnected cycles of storytelling modeling and coding.
And it is about learning and about making mistakes
So we have activities that focus on housing and documenting,
scenarios and modeling them, telling stories,
walking through them, refocus,
proposing models, explore the language
and take those models turn them into code to learn from that experiment
then go back to your scenarios
and model more scenarios and other cases and so on
So it's this constant whirlpool.
I think this model captures much better what is actually going on
in a DDD style development project.
on the other hand this model is not as neat as the one I showed you before it looks a bit messy
and maybe that is the reason why this metaphor is often
neglected. When people talk about DDD.
Yet, I think the more...
The more I think about it. The more I reflect on it. The more powerful this metaphor becomes for me.
And I mean it's easy to see that
When you highlight how often the term scenario or story appears
in the in the whirlpool that there's a connection to the main storytelling.
So for me
Domain Storytelling fills this gap of how to actually
gather my my scenarios how do I model them.
But how to return them? how bring...
How do I bring them closer to developing software?
So that's a way that Domain Storytelling can help with this model exploration whirlpool makes it more tangible
but it also had an influence on Domain Storytelling
because it helps me to better understand how to integrate
the main storytelling into the domain driven design process
and it helps me to choose the right scope for a story
so which level of granularity am I interested in
Am I analyzing the current process
or am I deciding a new process and so on
so I think this is very helpful for that
for choosing the right scope of a story
now the second aspect that
has influenced the main storytelling and the development of the method
is collaborative modeling
Before I became a DDD practitioner
and a DDD coach I was active in the academic modeling community
and the software and enterprise architecture communities
and in the requirements engineering community
and I always felt a bit like an outsider.
And one of the reasons why this is different with the DDD community is that
DDD practitioners have realized the value of collaborative modeling
While I had felt that for some time it really became evident to me
At explore DDD conference in the U.S. where Paul Rayner drew this picture.
It shows collaborative modeling is one of the most important concepts of DDD.
It's one of its pillars
So I felt right at home, of course.
While I'd felt that for some
time that collaborative modeling is
an important pillar of DDD
I think that many people use it synonymously with
EventStorming ever since Alberto Brandolini came up with it.
So I use EventStorming too. Here you see my colleagues
in a big picture EventStorming session
or some of my colleagues
and I think of it as
well I have a modeling toolbox
and in this toolbox there are several tools
like EventStorming and Domain Storytelling
and I think that
in many projects
you will have to use more than one modeling method
and you definitely have an advantage
if there are several tools in your toolbox and you know how to choose
between those tools and when to choose which tool
that will increase your changes your chance of success
Now thinking of it as a toolbox is one way of seeing it
but I think collaborative modeling could also be described as a family of methods
with different relationships between them and
the more I became experienced with DDD
and the more I looked at collaborative modeling as this family
So in my mind I would say that
by now I see software development as a series of conversations
that are aided by modeling
with different members of this collaborative modeling family so with different tools
The community behind those methods or tools
They've started to write a book
called the Visual Collaboration Tools book you can find it on leanpub
and download it from there
so this is a really thriving community
and it's great to see that this family is ever expanding
and to see new connections made between those tools
So this is definitely something that has influenced me a lot
Now the final thought I want to share with you today is
one of the most important concepts I think in DDD
and that is that language and models are bounded by their context
So this is really an eye opener
I mean words can mean different things to different people, right.
So even if those people work in the same organization they might have different ideas
For example in our movie theater what could ticket mean
So for one person it could be a sellable unit that generates a profit
and for the other person it could mean a piece of paper that is validated in order to grant access to a movie theater.
So if you look at this course-grade domain story from before again
Cashier might think of the ticket as something that they sell it has a price and so on.
and they are sure well they are not really interested in the price
they are just checking if it's the right date and time right movie and then the ground access
So they both say ticket but they mean different concepts when they mean "ticket".
Now this will often happen in
coarse-grained domain stories or also other
collaborative modelling techniques that when you have different stakeholders
to use the same terms without meaning exactly the same thing.
and this is not necessarily a problem
especially on this coarse-grained level.
but I'll I want to show you an example where it really was a problem for me
to moderate the modeling session
because there was an immediate problem
that luckily I could resolve with the help of bounded contexts
So this is yet another domain that tell you about this time it's a
fixtures company called awesome browser games
so a company that provides a platform for playing browser games
but it's based on a true story
so in the workshop in a real workshop we got different people from different departments together
domain expert, software developers
and we wanted to start with a course-grained domain story
that shows us an end-to-end process
so a first-time user signs up plays their first game gets built for the game
So someone started and say well the first step is that the user opens an account with awesome browser games
and immediately someone said no
they said no the account is much, is created much later, I know that for a fact
but the first person replied no no no no
you are wrong this is the first step I know it I know that for a fact
this is the first thing that we do we open the account
well in the words of Rartin Fowler
"A single conceptual model is a tricky beast to work with"
and that was what we were trying to do here build a single conceptual model
for terms that could not be reconciled
so bounded contexts to the rescue what did we do to resolve this situation move on forward
well I said okay let's assume for a moment that
the first person is right and that the account is open in the first step and then the continued modeling
and eventually arrived at the step here the step five in the picture
where the second person thinks that their account is created
and we used different icons to show that
we mean different things here so different kinds of accounts possibly
and when we talked about it it became evident
that one person thought about
the account in the context of use user registration
and the other person
was thinking about accounts in the context of
what we call the game management
so there are actually two kinds of accounts here.
one that are per user and the other one is per user and per game
so if you play different games you have different accounts one for each game
So luckily we had this
concept of bounded context that helped us to resolve this issue
otherwise I don't think the workshop would have been a success but with this
revelation and we could move on forward and had a successful workshop
and actually you can use this kind of differences in languages to
spot and find and identify bounded context
so that's also a way how we use Domain Storytelling for finding bounded contexts
You've actually seen another example already where
we used bounded context and we remodeled them in a domain story
and that was of course the cinema example
So again on the left in the coursed-grain story we see in the rectangles different contexts
So we have ticket sales and snack sales and entrance control
and in the more detailed domain story
that story plays within one context within the ticket sales context
and of course we want to make sure that within the ticket sales context
we have the same idea of the of the terms that are used there so
that we need our ubiquitous language right
So these are the three things where I think
DDD has really influenced Domain Storytelling
and influenced its development and also my personal modeling practices
So we have this idea of the model exploration whirlpool
a powerful metaphor a bit neglected in the DDD community sadly
and we have this this big big community of collaborative modeling
that is not only within DDD but also extending to other communities
like behavior different development for example
and we have this game-changing concept of bounded context
so the idea that language and models are bounded by the context
that really changed my modeling practices.
Now if you want to know more about Domain Storytelling
go check out domainstorytelling.org
You will find my slides on speaker deck
and now I'm looking forward for your questions, thank you.
Okay thank you very much about Dr. Stefan Hofer's sharing.
and right now let me see what's question that the participants asked.
so there are a lot of questions on slido right
Yeah! okay. Can you see my screen?
Yes, I can.
Okay the first question is
I saw there is no round-trip between each components,
could you tell us what motivated you to
create this 1-way direction to express the message flow?
So I think this question refers to the
roadwork construction example that I gave
if I'm correct
um yeah so um
This is something very typical for software developers
we often think in this kind of request response
a pattern um or yeah or like you
you call a method and then you get a return value or something like that
I mean you can use the main storytelling in that way
but often I think it's the better idea to
to use it to express an intention.
otherwise the the picture becomes very messy with a lot of
back and forth, and back and forth, and back and forth without really gaining
without pushing the story forward
so the idea is that you express intention
and not necessarily things like
you know you enter something in the system in the web page you press the button
and then the web page renders a new html page and then you press the next button
and then it renders a new html page
this would be very boring that's not a good story
there's not a lot of information in it that's that drives the conversation forward
so that's what I want to avoid and I focus more on
what is the intention of this step
and then it's okay to have just a one-way information flow
or one way direction
yeah so that's that's the idea.
Okay, thank you for your answer.
And the second question is
have you ever met someone asking about the compression
between domain story telling and even storming?
How do you think about it?
Again that is a very common question
and as you saw in the in the slides
I put one picture of our event stopping session in there
that I facilitated
so I use both methods
plus many more
I would say for the last
three years or so I've used event storming and Domain Storytelling about
to the same amount like 50 50 something like that
there is an overlap
there are situations where you can use one or the other and will still get a good result out of it
but there are also situations where I think one is better than the other
and one of the indicators for me is
what is this process about or
what information are you looking to
to learn what what are interested in
if it's about many people collaborating with each other
so if you have a business process it involves
many people or even many software systems
and information goes from one person to the next and back
and you're interested in the communication patterns
and and learning how people collaborate
then I think
Domain Storytelling is the better approach
because the story is centered around the the people around the actors
and you can really see who is doing what
with whom
if on the other hand you're more interested in this time series
like in evenstorming you have this timeline from left to right
and status changes
and this happened better and that happened that happened
then event storming is is I think the better approach
but as I said um
I use I use both there are situations where you can use both
and you can also combine it
for example in the project that I'm currently working on
we started with Domain Storytelling to figure out the the process
that this new software system should build
and then the development team decided they want to implement the software using event sourcing
so for big picture level we had domain stories
and for design level for the system design
we switched to event storming because it fits much better to an event-sourced way of building systems
there are more ways to combine it I have to refer you to the book for that
we have a couple of examples there
yeah so
Okay, thank you very much.
Okay, the third question is
can Domain Storytelling be used as a methodlogy
or a tool for class design in the impolementation of DDD tactical design?
I think there was a follow-up from
Kim in the in the chat
so it depends on different perspective and how much focus you're looking
for in time series consequences or the actors relationships yes yes I think that's right
that's uh it's a good summary
Okay now to the next question sorry.
So can the Domain Storytelling be used as a methodology or a tool for class design.
Yes, it can.
The funny thing about it is that
Domain Storytelling well its predecessors are actually rather old
so the first ancestor the first predecessor is from the 1990s
and it was heavily influenced by object oriented modeling
so you can still still see that influence and
I think it is suitable as a tool for class modeling
when you want an object oriented approach
and it also fits nicely into the the DDD thinking
because you can look at the work objects and say okay
this is going to be either an entity or aggregate or maybe a value object
and the arrows that depict the activities
well those are the um
that is the behavior of the entities and the work objects
so for example
in this construction example we had permits and we had hearings
and the hearing was started then statements um are considered
and these are all the things that later become entities and aggregates
so a hearing for example we model the hearing as an aggregate
and and stuff like that so that works
What do you need for that you need Domain Storytelling that you.
Sorry, you need domain stories that are rather fine-grained
so if you're on a very overview level this wouldn't work
but if if you model it rather fine-drained
then you have enough language and enough expressiveness in the model
that you can defer object-oriented design from that
Okay, thank you very much.
and the next question is
Domain Storytelling as a methodology of implementing DDD
what do you think is advantage? and what about the disadvantage?
Most of the time I used Domain Storytelling as a communication tool
and the thing that is
apart from what I just explained from that from the previous question with
how you can use it to implement it
but mostly um
I think it's about bringing people people together
having meaningful conversations about the domain
and that is something that Domain Storytelling is uh really good at helping with this
so this would be the the main advantage
and um
then you can drive the conversation into different directions for example you can use it to find uh
bounded contexts so that would be a typical way of using it
uh to implement DDD
or you can use it on a lower level
to to come up with object oriented
design using entities and aggregates and so on
What about disadvantages?
Well I'm a bit biased here of course I really love Domain Storytelling so
it's it's hard to think about disadvantages but
now with the feedback
Okay, but well maybe let's put it this way
It's not the right tool for everything
So that's why I always talk about this toolbox
and I've had situations where
I thought using this this modeling method is a good idea
and then we go into the workshop and it just doesn't work
for some reason for for whatever reason
and then it's always good if you have this toolbox of other modeling tools and say
okay I'm sorry this conversation is not going forward
but I have an idea
let's use for example
let's use example mapping to to to figure that out or
let's use event storming and then you can switch
so I think this would be a disadvantage like
treating it as a one-size-fits-all tool for every situation that's not going to work
you you will need different tools in your toolbox
Okay and the next is
Domain Storytelling suitable as a DDD implementation method in complex domain
such as the banking or financial industry.
Yes, I think so that it's suitable for complex domains
my colleagues and I have have used this technique
and its predecessors for
uh 15 years and we applied it in
complex domains like healthcare,
banking, insurance
managing ports for example
we had stuff like
disaster management disaster disaster response teams
so a whole lot of different domains logistics of course
e-commerce so it's not really
bound to one domain it's really for for
pretty much every domain
so I have not encountered a domain yet where I say okay this doesn't fit here
yeah so I would definitely to say this is usable in complex domains
Okay, thank you for your presentation
Have you run into a suitable where one object
can either be a working object
or an actor in different sequence of one DST image?
How do we deal with it?
That's a good question. It's already a bit advanced
so well
Within the domain, of course, it can happen that.
in in one domain story something is an actor and in one domain is something is a work object.
similarly to in in one bounded context
you can model something as an entity
and in the next bounded context it's a value object because it doesn't change
so that's possible
but this question is about in the same picture in the same domain
again this is not a common case but it can happen
for example um
if we think about something like
user management, user registration you sign up for something
you are the user you're the actor then
I'm only as an actor
and you open your account
and then the system
creates a user as a representation
of the of the human being
then we have
user as an actor and then we have user as a work object with the same picture
but that's not a problem at all
you just have to use a different icon
to represent that.
So I would use this little stick figure for the for the actor for the person
and for example the icon set that I use that's the google material I can set
they have another smaller picture of a user with a little check mark
and that's the one that I typically use for stuff like
um user account
So that's that's the way how I deal with it.
So use different icons to represent those different concepts
and then it works.
Okay!
as the realization of products or services,
what methodologies or tool does Domain Storytelling usually integrate
with to form a complete agile development process
from requirements analysis to system development
um very nice so um
one of the tools of the methods that I use
um a lot in combination with Domain Storytelling
is user story mapping
why
because of two reasons so
Domain Storytelling is always about scenarios so about typically